Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. Presbytery of Washington City Records
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. Presbytery of Washington City records 1823-1950
MSS36830
Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. Presbytery of Washington City
21 items
11 containers
4.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Regional association of Presbyterian churches in Washington, D.C., and vicinity in Virginia and Maryland. Proceedings of the Presbytery of Washington City and its predecessors, the Presbytery of the District of Columbia and the Presbytery of the Potomac, concerning the administration and establishment of churches in the Washington, D.C., region. Includes an historical volume summarizing proceedings and the history of the presbyteries.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
Organizations
Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. (New School). Presbytery of the District of Columbia; Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. Presbytery of Potomac.; Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. Presbytery of Washington City.
Subjects
Depressions--1929.; Influenza Epidemic, 1918-1919--United States.; Presbyterian Church--Maryland.; Presbyterian Church--Virginia.; Presbyterian Church--Washington (D.C.); World War, 1914-1918--Religious aspects.; World War, 1939-1945--Religious aspects.
Places
Maryland--Church history.; United States--Economic conditions--1918-1945.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Religious aspects.; Virginia--Church history.; Washington (D.C.)--Church history.
Provenance
The records of the Presbytery of Washington City, a regional association of Presbyterian churches in Washington, D.C., and vicinity in Maryland and Virginia, were given to the Library of Congress by the Presbytery in 1941 and 1956.
Access and Restrictions
The records of Presbytery of Washington City Records are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Presbytery of Washington City span the years 1823-1950 and include records of two predecessor organizations, the Presbytery of the District of Columbia, 1823-1870, and the Presbytery of the Potomac, 1858-1870. The two presbyteries combined in 1870 to form the Presbytery of Washington City, a precursor of the present presbytery, the National Capital Presbytery.
These records consist of the proceedings of the presbyteries. Churches documented in Maryland include congregations in Bethesda, Bladensburg, Darnestown, First Constitutional Church in Baltimore, Granite, Lisbon, Mount Airy, Poolesville, Quarries, Ridge (Carroll County), Rockville, and the United States Naval Academy at Annapolis. Virginia churches documented include those in Alexandria, Falls Church, and Lewinsville. Several Presbyterian churches in the District of Columbia are also documented.
The proceedings record the response of the presbyteries to the Civil War, World War I, the influenza epidemic of 1918-1919, the Great Depression, and World War II. An historical volume at the end of the collection summarizes the events and trends reflected by the proceedings.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Container List
- Presbytery of the District of Columbia (Box 1)
  - Oct. 1823-Apr. 1866, (2 vols.) (Box 1)
  - Oct. 1866-June 1870 (Box 2)
- Presbytery of the Potomac, Oct. 1858-June 1870 (Box 2)
- Presbytery of Washington City (Box 3)
  - June 1870-Oct. 1884, (2 vols.) (Box 3)
  - Apr. 1884-Dec. 1890, (2 vols.) (Box 4)
  - Apr. 1891-June 1901, (2 vols.) (Box 5)
  - Oct. 1901-Oct. 1913, (2 vols.) (Box 6)
  - Oct. 1913-Mar. 1920, (2 vols.) (Box 7)
  - Apr. 1920-Mar. 1927, (2 vols.) (Box 8)
  - Apr. 1927-June 1936, (2 vols.) (Box 9)
  - Sept. 1936-Nov. 1950, (2 vols.) (Box 10)
  - Roll and index (Box 11)
  - Miscellany (Box 11)